SENIOR PHYSICAL SCIENTIST

Summary

Transformational leader with great knowledge of the Environmental, Safety and Health (EHS) area with over 16 years experience. Environmental Management System ISO Std 14001 coordinator/auditor for over seven years, first qualified coordinator/auditor since inception of the program. Conducted the first-ever internal audit at the installation, met deadline set by federal government. Briefed findings from audits (internal/external) at cross-function team meetings and to wing leadership, tracked all discrepancies to closure. Developed first ever air sampling strategy for E-3 Sentry Airborne Warning & Control Systems; able to purchase calibration gas locally, saved the Air Force over 80K. Co-Authored deployment rotation health risk data exposure form, annotated all exposures protected over 5,000 deployed personnel. Guided/mentored over 125 enlisted members to selection for promotion and awards with 17 years' supervisory experience. Conducted first-ever joint Environmental Health Site Assessment report while deployed to Balad AB, IRAQ; annotated/classified all hazards to all personnel. Total asset manager with multi-disciplined skills and ability to quickly adapt in diverse environments. Articulate communicator and facilitator whose candor and integrity will deliver "bottom line" solution sets necessary to achieve desired outcomes. Self-motivated; able to pursue projects to completion while managing other responsibilities. Tactical risk manager who negotiates bureaucratic, legal, contractual and ethical mine fields to successful completion of the mission-focused plan.

Skills

- Effective team leader
- Strong verbal communicator
 Detail-oriented
- Strategic planning
- Decision-making ability
- Data interpretation and analysis
- Self-motivated
- Dedicated

Experience

Senior Physical Scientist 06/2009 to Current US Air Force City, STATE

- Prepared briefings for cross-functional team meetings.
- Educated contractor personnel on environmental standards for each applicable projects.
- Properly managed four (3 credit card/1 check)Â different environmental accounts for office, created/matched orders for monthly reports and annual audits.
- Reviewed and edited correspondence for all environmental plans and meeting minutes prior to submission for signature.
- Served as the principal environmental representative for all emergency response matters, training and clean-up related.
- Monitored multiple databases, Â kept track of all environmental data (14 areas) Â and 6 permits.
- Led cross-functional teams to develop aspect inventory and action plans.
- Audited all 17 areas of the ISO Standard 14001 program elements per year and offered recommendations for improvements.
- Bolstered Environmental Management System program, briefed at wing meetings and enlisted leadership support attuned to program.
- Trained over 200 personnel on environmental assessment checklists; responsibilities/requirements met.
- Trained 10 different shops on Air permit requirements; ensured personnel aware of their requirements.
- Developed Environmental Management System pamphlet for base distribution to increase program awareness (ISO Std 14001).
- Utilized unit training managers to boost required base environmental training statistics; percentage trained increased by over 70%.
- Conducted installation's 1st-ever Environmental Management System internal audit; coordinated with applicable agencies and provided/briefed report to base leadership.
- Ensured base was in full conformance by 2009 deadline, met Air Force & ISO Std 14001 requirements.
- Maintained/administered environmental database/SharePoint site for entire flight of over 50 personnel.
- Consolidated 30 facility construction permits; eliminated unnecessary tracking requirements.
- Managed Air Quality programs and permits; ensured all deadlines met, no Notices of Violations.
- Maintained and operated the Environmental Quality Data Calls for entire base (twice a year), gathered all required data from applicable agencies; ensured all deadlines were met.

Superintendent, Bioenvironmental Engineering 10/2005 to 02/2009 US Air Force City, STATE

- Delivered risk communication and occupational health support to Air Force personnel for all environmental and occupational health programs.
- Revived Balad AB air sampling program; collected 100+ samples for Dioxin/Furans from burn pit, utilized results for inclusion in personnel medical records.
- Co-Authored Balad deployment health risk data exposure form, annotated all exposures; protected over 5,000 deployed personnel.
- Accomplished over 500Å activity assessments; quantified physical/chemical hazards for all chemical and physical agents and recommended controls, safeguarded base populace of over 6,000.
- Verified and recommended safety equipment such as hearing protection and respirators were available to employees; monitored the use of such equipment to ensure proper fit and protection.
- Reviewed physicians' reports/conducted worker studies; determined whether disease/illness are job-related.
- Prepared and reviewed specifications and orders for purchase of safety equipment, ensuring that proper features are present and that items conformed to health and safety standards.
- Conducted first-ever joint Environmental Health Site Assessment report while deployed to Balad AB, IRAQ; annotated/classified all hazards personnel were exposed to, Â report sent to headquarters.
- Team player, joined forces with the Army taught Air Emissions block for Field Sanitation Team training in deployed location.
- Organized comprehensive WVA; identified classified risks; briefed/coordinated WVA to FPWG/ITWG

- Identified water tower contamination (HAPSITE); co-developed sampling plan/coordinate w/base agencies
- Point of Contact for OSHA Voluntary Protection Program visit; encapsulated Air Force wingman and Air Force Smart Operations 21 concepts base wide.
- Guided office of 12 technicians on completion of over 80 special surveys; reduced overdue surveys by 50%.
- Surveyed 1,380 industrial specific operations ensured compliance with laws/sustained healthy areas.
- Evaluated situations where a workers refused to work in hazardous environment and determined how best to eliminate applicable hazards.

Superintendent, Medical Operations Squadron 02/2004 to 02/2005 US Air Force City, STATE

- Managed activities of 150 military, civilians & contract medical personnel over eight diverse flights.
- Accomplished comprehensive enlisted force management reviews focused on efficiency, productivity, teamwork, morale, self-analysis, and strategic insight which focused outcomes on mission effectiveness and improved readiness statistics.
- Guided/mentored 125 enlisted members to selection for promotion and awards.
- Project officer for Health Service Inspection; provided occupational health program executive oversight.
- Implemented the publication and transmission of Squadron Commander's weekly roll call notes to over 200 personnel.
- Monitored trends for over 200 personnel, briefed commander on any adverse issues/concerns.

Superintendent, Medical Support Squadron 02/2003 to 02/2004 US Air Force City, STATE

- Managed team of over 80 medical professionals.
- Served as mentor to over 50 enlisted team members.
- Monitored patient complaints, ensured all complaints were handled with care and empathy.
- Participated in unit based Quality Assurance Program.
- Prepared for HIPAA and JCAHO reviews, ensured required brochures and pamphlets were available to patients in all clinics.
- Ensured HIPAA compliance.
- Advised section leadership on organizational policy matters and recommend needed changes.
- Monitored squadron for adverse trends and briefed findings to commander.

Education and Training

M.S: Occupational Safety & Health Columbia Southern University Occupational Safety & Health

B.S: Occupational Safety & Health Columbia Southern University Occupational Safety & Health

B.S: Environmental Management Columbia Southern University Environmental Management

Skills

Air Force, Â Civil Engineering, Â Environmental Health, Â Hazardous Material, Inspection, Â Audit, Â ISO Std 14001, Leadership, Â Mentor, Communicator, Occupational Safety & Health, Â Quality, Safety, Strategic, Supervisory, Teamwork, Customer Service, Emergency Response, OSHA, Industrial Hygiene.